<root><page>118v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f242.item</image>


<div>
<id>p118v_a1</id>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<ab>For the best <sup>result</sup>, it is necessary to [words missing] sand used in the core rather than using it in the <sup>frame</sup>, until it no longer escapes.</ab>
<head>Excellent sand</head>


<ab>Get some of the same sand, the finest that you can, for covering the medal.</ab>






</div>
<div>
<id>p118v_b2</id>
<head>Casting in a <tl>frame</tl></head>


<ab>The same sand which has been used in composed heated cores, i.e. of <m>plaster</m>, <m>brick</m> and <fr><m>alum de plume</m></fr>, is excellent for casting in <tl>frames</tl>, and I have tried it as follows. I crushed the pieces which had come out of <tl>core molds</tl> in a <tl>mortar</tl>, <tl>pestling</tl> slowly, because this sand is very soft. I did not pass it through a <tl>sieve</tl>, because the <fr><m>alum de plume</m></fr> mixed in, which makes it bind together, would not pass through. But I did refine upon <tl>marble</tl> what seemed to me too coarse, and having thus prepared it, I moistened it with the <m>salt ammoniac water</m> made of <m>sal ammoniac</m> the size of two <ms><pa>walnuts</pa></ms>, in a bottle of <m>common water</m> the size of a <tl>bottle</tl> in which one boils <m>barley water</m>, or in a good <tl>pot</tl> of <m>water</m>. You should find the <m>water</m> fairly salty. I mixed in half a <ms>glass</ms> of <m>sal ammoniac</m> two <tl>silver spoonfuls</tl> of <m>spirits</m>. Having thus moistened the sand in order to give it a nice hold, though it still came apart easily, I sprinkled my medal with <m>pulverized charcoal</m> with a <tl>file</tl> to remove the <m>grease</m>, and all other <m>fat</m>. One must avoid these, since they hinder good stripping. I blew on the medal and molded it, and with the female part of the <tl>frame</tl> full, I marked and made a line on the back and edge of the medal, and on the nearby sand as well. In order that the second <tl>frame</tl> take the imprint thereupon to indicate the place for making the cast, I uncovered the contour of the medal and pounced the whole side with <m>pulverized charcoal</m>, and then I filled the male part with sand. I separated the <tl>frame</tl> and did not strike the corners of the medal to make it strip, since that cracks the sand and makes it come apart. But I did strike the back of the <tl>frame</tl>, holding the place of the medal on the bottom, and it <tl>molded</tl> very cleanly. If it hadn't stripped thus, I would have waited to remove it until the <tl>frame</tl> had been dried out over heat. I lit a row of <m>charcoal</m> between two little <tl>trivets</tl> of <m>iron</m> in the form that you see, and put the back of the <tl>frame</tl> thereupon, and the imprint on top, since in this way, they dry out slowly. And if, by chance, they should crack from being too moistened, it's on the back that they take the harshest heat, and the imprint remains safe and whole. </ab>
 
<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
For medals and flat things, the true heat of lead and tin. That is when it is melted gently.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Note that I filled the frame before pressing, and did not strike it, but pressed it with the strength of my <bp>hands</bp> alone, since striking it may distort it. Make sure that your frame does not move at all, and if you put some moistened sand under it, it will only hold in place more firmly.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Make a cast that is not too thick, as not to weigh the medal down, but cast wide enough over the medal that it covers the third part. Do not forget the vents.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Drying frames means removing their dampness, so that they do not smoke any longer, though they be very hot.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
To heat is to redden the frame, which is done for <m>gold</m> and for <m>silver</m>.</note> 
</div></root>