<root><page>100r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f205.image</image>


<div>
<id>p100r_1</id>
<head><m>Gold</m> color</head>


<ab>To very quickly make a matte layer of <m>gold</m> on canvas or other <m>oil</m> paintings, thick <m>nut oil</m> is made under the sun or on the fire as previously mentioned, since it thickens by itself in this way, even if it does not have any <m>lead</m>, nor any <m>ceruse</m>. And with it, grind <m>massicot</m>, <m>mine</m>, and other drying substances, but not <m>vert-de-gris</m> nor <m>orpiment</m>, since they make the <m>gold</m> fade. It will soon be dry. However, if the weather is not fair and dry, do not [...], because if the weather is musty and humid, the gold will blacken.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p100r_2</id>
<head>Lifelike portraiture</head>


<ab>One must carefully observe the eyes, the nose, and the beard, since these three things make the portrayal more lifelike.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p100r_3</id>
<head><m>Gemstones</m></head>


<ab>It is necessary to pound your materials in a thick <m>glass</m> mortar, set with <m>mastic</m> into another mortar, this one of <m>wood</m>, so that it does not break, this can be useful to <pro>perfumers</pro>, and the pestle has to be of <m>glass</m> too.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p100r_6</id>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<head><m>Glass</m> mortar and table for grinding</head>
</div>


<div>
<id>p100r_4</id>
<head>Vitrified <m>saltpeter</m></head>


<ab>
Melted with <m>stones</m>, it makes the <m>glass</m> very white. But one needs to quickly calcine it on a tile or hot shovel. And mix what remains of the vapor with as much white, calcined <m>stones</m>. It is true that, in the little oven, it does not clarify very well. But for big windows, it makes the <m>glass</m> very clear, white and clean.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p100r_5</id>
<head>Windows through which the sun does not pass</head>


<ab>Take the aforementioned calcined <m>saltpeter</m> and expose it to the air or to a humid place, and it will become a liquor which, if you rub both sides of the windows with it, the sun will not pass through at all, and it will create shade. One needs to put the <m>saltpeter</m> on some clean, flat surface, and put glowing <m>coals</m> on it, and keep it like that all over until the fire goes out.</ab>
 
<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
It is also used for melting and for mixing with <m>alkali salt</m> for cleaning hands.</note>
</div></root>