<root><page>067r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f139.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p066v_4</id>
<ab>
daylight, pull out with the tip of your fingernails the <m>hairs</m> which make the point too long, until the point seems good to you, and when you notice the <al>rat</al> <m>hairs</m> that are entirely black and the <m>hairs</m> of the same <al>squirrel</al> that are whitish from their root to their middle. When it pleases you, tie and hold it tight with a thread in two places, then cut that <sup>the <m>hairs</m></sup> which is superfluous and fit it to a quill whose size is appropriate, of a <al>duck</al> or a <al>crow</al> for the small ones. The good brushes are those that, having been dipped into <m>water</m>, do not collapse if you try to trace it on your hand.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p067r_1</id>
<head><m>Oil</m></head>


<ab>All <m>oils</m>, which are absorbed in <m>paper</m> and when warmed evaporate in the fire and leave a clear <m>paper</m> just like <m>turpentine</m> and <m>aspic oil</m>, are good for varnishing.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p067r_2</id>
<head>Sand</head>


<ab>All distempered and crushed things swell, according to some people.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p067r_3</id>
<head>Furnace with bellows</head>


<ab>Before you put the <m>metal</m> in, it must be red at the center like a <m>charcoal</m> and well lit. After, you fill it and cover the <m>charcoal</m> and adjust the bellows, otherwise the <m>metal</m> on the top will melt as a result of the bellows and its center will be curdled and will recool and will not run. But if you proceed in this manner you will melt everything you like.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p067r_4</id>
<head>Varnish on <m>paper</m></head>


<ab>The <pl>Germans</pl> make boxes covered with painted <m>paper</m> and varnish them with <m>egg white</m> mixed with <m>gum</m> and a little <m>oil</m>, not with <m>aspic</m>, but with another odorant which looks like <m>olive oil</m>. All the work done with <m>egg white</m> will hold <m>oil</m>. It is with this that <pro>painters</pro> trick the poor peasants, painting their bands of <m>taffeta</m> with this <m>egg white</m> to finish sooner. But the first rain will ruin everything.</ab>
</div></root>