<root><page>068r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f141.image</image>


<div>
<id>p068r_a1</id>
<head>Fancy tables</head>


<ab>You can make various hollow compartments and put in them fishes painted in color on simple <m>cardboard</m> left plain or, if you wish, on burnished <m>silver paper</m> to represent the scales. Afterwards, seal the grooves with translucent <m>lantern horn</m>. You can apply the same to other works.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p068r_a2</id>
<head>Planting trees</head>


<ab> They should be planted in dry weather, and gather a lot of earth all around the foot, in the form of a mound, so that the rain won't fill the pits and drown the trees.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p068r_a3</id>
<head>Casting</head>


<ab>I have tried four kinds of <m>sand</m> for <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m>: <m>chalk</m>, crushed <m>glass</m>, <m>tripoli</m> and burnt <m>linen</m>, all four are excellent. As to the <m>chalk</m>, it needs to be of the softest kind available, like the <m>Champagne chalk</m> used by <pro>painters</pro>. It releases very cleanly, needs not be dampened with <m>magistry</m> or with anything else, but is used in its natural dry state and finely pulverized. The first cast is always cleaner, however it will sustain two or three castings. Should you only cast once, keep in mind, while remaking your box mold, to take powdered <m>chalk</m> that has not yet been used, since the one previously used in the box has dried out and will not bind and hold together as well as fresh <m>chalk</m>. Crushed <m>glass</m> can be made from ordinary <m>glass sand</m>, however <m>cristallo glass</m> is more excellent, because <m>common glass</m> contains <m>saltwort</m> only, while <m>cristallo glass</m> contains both <m>salt of tartar</m> and <m>saltwort</m>. Both of them help the fusion, during which the glass is calcinated and reduced to its prime matter. In order to calcinate it perfectly, throw your pieces of <m>glass</m>, of whichever sort, among the largest possible glowing <m>coals</m>, unless some other violent heat source is available. And once the glass is red hot, throw it into <m>water</m>.</ab>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
<m>Putty</m> is considered excellent for these two <m>metals</m>.</note>
<cont/>
</div></root>