<root><page>011r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f26.item</image>


<div>
<id>p011r_1</id>
<head>How to <m>oil</m> paint <m>azure enamel</m></head>


<ab>This is a secret hardly known to common <pro>painters</pro>. Some take the finest they can and grind it with some <m>ceruse</m>, which binds it, and then prick with an awl in several places the areas they want to paint with <m>azure enamel</m>, so that the <m>oil</m> soaks into it in drops, not allowing the <m>azure</m>, which alone is heavy, to run. Others lay the painting flat and apply the <m>azure</m> and that can be also soaked. The most important is to grind it well on <m><tl>marble</tl></m>, and before that, to have rinsed it. Some grind it thoroughly with an <m>egg yolk</m> and then rinse it five or six times and apply it not with a paint <tl>brush</tl>, which would be too soft, but with a <tl>brush</tl> highly softened and curled, and laying it down thickly as if you were applying it with a <tl>trowel</tl>, it settles even and flat. I experimented <sup>and found</sup> that grinding <m>azur enamel</m> with <m>egg yolk</m> and then rinsing it in <m>water</m> is good. However it does lose a little vividness when ground. I also rinsed it successively in <m>water</m> and, after letting it stand, I extracted some <m>blue water</m> with a <tl>sponge</tl> and pressed it into another <tl>vessel</tl> where it was left to stand, and from the residue I obtained the dust, <pa>flower</pa> and finest part of the <m>azure</m> without grinding it, which is the best way, because it loses some of its color when ground. Those who make it in <pl>Germany</pl> compose it like <m>enamel</m>, in large pieces which they pound, pass through several <tl>sieves</tl> and rinse.</ab>


<ab>To make <m>azures</m> beautiful, they wash them or soak them in <m>rock water</m>, as they call it, which is <m>water</m> distilled from mines where <m>azure</m> or <m><fr>vert d'azur</fr></m> is found, either distilled naturally through the mountain's veins or distilled with an <tl>alembic</tl> from <m>azure</m> or <m>copper</m> mineral stones.</ab>


<ab><m>Azure dust</m> is not good for landscapes because it fades with <m>oil</m>. Only true <m>azure</m> holds. <m>Azure enamel</m>cannot be worked if it is too thick. Therefore, try it on your <bp>fingernail</bp> or your <m>oil</m> <sup>color</sup> palette. If it is sandy, grind it only with <m>egg yolk</m> or, even better, rinse it in <m>clear water</m> and with a <tl>sponge</tl> extract the <m>colored water</m> after it starts to sink, and in this way you will extract the finest <pa>flower</pa>, which will be easy to work with.</ab>
</div></root>