<root><page>124r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f253.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p124r_a1</id>
<head><m>Hairy animals</m> and very thin delicate <m>flowers</m></head>


<ab>It is difficult to mold <m>hairy animals</m> because <m>hairs</m> raise up and come out looking mixed and entangled. Therefore, it is necessary to keep it laid down with a drying agent and which makes it firmer, and the best thing to use is <m>wheat oil</m>, with which you will anoint it. Once cast, you will be able to repair it. The bodies of <m>butterflies</m> or of <m>herbs</m> that have a <m>stem</m> and <m>leaves</m> that are rugged with downy and lanuginous <m>hairs</m> must also be anointed in the same <m>oil</m> to keep this foliage laid down. With these, <m>flowers</m> that have very delicate and thin <m>leaves</m> because dry <m>wheat oil</m> straightens them and makes them firm. And, If someone brags to [be able to] cast anything that will be given to them, give them to cast the  fuzzy head of the herb called <m>dandelion</m> or a <m>papus</m>@, which comes from the seeds of <m>lapasses</m> @ and takes flight at the slightest sigh of wind.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p124r_a1</id>
<head>Noyaulx for molding hollow</head>


<ab><m>Gold</m> and <m>silver animals</m> are often cast hollow to avoid heaviness and for the cost as well, if they are not rather small. But in order to make the core and the noyau, the mold must be freshly molded and not dry.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p124r_a3</id>
<head><m>Spider web</m> </head>


<ab>It comes undone in <m>water</m> and even so it cannot be molded as a core, but one casts the <m>spider</m> and then one draws the stretched <m>filaments</m> among the <m>grass</m> like they [the spiders] do in the fields on some <m>thick paper</m> with a needle. One makes an edge around of <m>paper</m> glued to the <m>thick paper</m> and one casts with <m>tin</m> mixed with very little <m>lead</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p124r_a4</id>
<head>Fine <m>gold</m> </head>


<ab>There is a kind of <m>gold</m> which, even though it is very fine and unalloyed, is passed through <m>aqua fortis</m> and <m>antimony</m>, it is however so brittle that it cannot withstand the hammer. And the mixture of <m>verdigris</m> mentioned above [that is used] to make <m>gold</m> flow, will make it as soft as <m>lead</m>.</ab></div></root>