<root><page>124v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f254.image</image>
<div>
<id>p124v_1</id>


<head><m>rouge clair</m> <m>enamel</m></head>


<ab>Pure <m>gold</m> does not work well with enamel because the <m>enamel</m> remains yellowish. Alloyed <m>gold</m>, such as that of escu or pistolet coins, works better. The pale color of pure <m>gold</m> makes the enamel seem faded. That is why you must heat it again after being cut to make it reddish so that the <m>enamel</m> will be beautiful, otherwise it will be dull.</ab>


<ab>A kind of light <m>rouge clair</m> which, scratched with sand, will lose its beauty.</ab>


<ab>There are some with <m>gold</m> grains in it. And also, good <pro>goldsmiths</pro> agree that the good one is made with <m>gold</m>.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p124v_2</id>
 
<head>Casting <m>gold</m></head>


<ab>Molds are better reheated in a closed furnace like a reverberatory one. <pro>Goldsmiths</pro> who want to cast an important work which has taken much effort to be modeled in <m>wax</m>, put the molds into a pot, and they coat and fill the pot with <m>earth</m> that withstands fire, in which the molds are tightly packed. Then they reheat the mold, the <m>earth</m> and the pot all together; when they are all red, they cast the <m>gold</m>. Fine <m>gold</m> does not flow but alloyed <m>gold</m> flows well.</ab>


<note><m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m> do not get acid if red and hot and dipped into <m>water</m>.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>gold</m> is a quarter heavier than <m>lead</m>.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
When <m>gold</m> gets the right heat it becomes green like emerald.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Be sure that, int the forge where you want to cast <m>gold</m>, no <m>lead</m>, <m>tin</m>, or <m>lime</m> has dripped in.</note>
</div>
<div>
<id>p124v_3</id>


<head>Way to cast small <al>lizards</al></head>


<ab>Because you always have to cast by the tail, and because it is fragile and thin metal will flow with difficulty, even when the tail is folded, roll wax in little nets of this size. Apply some [wax] with a hot iron wire, as we say, one [drip] at the end of the tail and to the other parts of the tail, from one side to the other, such as shown. Be sure that you do not apply <m>wax</m> on the animal, otherwise the sand from the second cast would not touch these parts.  Be sure that the end of the wax aligns with the end of the empty part of the first cast. Be sure to also make wax conduits around the legs and around the edges of the body, which are longuish, and you will fill the mold through these pipes. Follow the above.</ab>
 
<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
When the tail - which is fragile and closer to the cast - peels off easily, the rest will also peel easily.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
The most important is that the ears of the snake are well casted.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Do a very fine cast on the intake of the animal, as thick as a knife.</note>


<figure/>
<cont/>
</div></root>