<root>﻿<page>004v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f14.image</image>


</div>
<div>
<id>p004v_a1</id>
<head><m>Black</m> <m>varnish</m> for sword guards, [<m>metal</m>] bands for chests, etc.</head>
 
<ab>Take <m>linseed oil</m> or, for a cheaper option, <m>walnut oil</m>, and rid it of fat with <m>garlic cloves</m> and <m>hog’s fennel</m> (some also add <m>bread crusts</m>), which you will boil in it for a good quarter of an hour. Then add to one pound of the <m>oil</m> boiled in this way a piece of <m>black pitch</m> the size of a walnut and as much <m>wheat</m> as can be cupped in two hands , without removing the <m>garlic</m> and <m>onions</m>, and allow to boil together for a good quarter of an hour. Once the <m>pitch</m> is well melted and the <m>oil</m> takes on body, you can remove it from the fire. Then, to varnish, place your <m>iron</m> over a warm <m>charcoal</m> fire and apply with a feather or a brush. When you see that it no longer smokes, it is done and your <m>varnish</m> is dry.</ab>
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
For an excellent <m>black</m> <m>varnish</m>, add two or three <m>paternoster beads</m> to the rest.</note>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
Some consider <m>walnut oil</m> to be better.</note>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
If there is a quantity of <m>varnish</m>, it needs to boil for at least half a day, because the more it boils, the better it is. Should the <m>varnish</m> boil over, it is dangerous for it to catch fire and it is difficult to extinguish. So do this in a courtyard or other open space.</note>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
In five or six lbs. of <m>oil</m>, one must put one lb. of <m>galipot</m>, which costs 4 sols, and some peeled <m>garlic cloves</m>. This <m>varnish</m> is not black in and of itself, but turns black when exposed to <m>fire</m>.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
See below, around the 3rd part of this book, after <m>sands</m>, in the chapter on <pro>furbishers</pro>.</note>


</div>
<div>
<id>p004v_a2</id>
<head>Black <m>varnish</m> without fire, without disassembling harnesses or removing [<m>metal</m>] bands from chests.</head>


<ab>Take <m>spike lavender oil varnish</m> and mix it with <m>charcoal black</m> or <m>lampblack</m> and, without fire, it will mix in by itself. Apply the <m>varnish</m> with a brush and it will soon be dry. <m>Turpentine varnish</m> would work quite well but it does not dry as quickly.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p004v_a3</id>
<head><pro>Iron engravers’</pro> <m>varnish</m>.</head>


<ab>Take <m>linseed oil</m> or <m>walnut oil</m> and instead of <m>black pitch</m> you will add some <m>pine resin</m> and you must cook it like <m>black varnish</m> on fire. And to apply it, heat your <m>iron</m> and apply just one layer of <m>varnish</m>, and when it no longer smokes, it is dry. Then engrave with a <m>steel</m> point whatever you want. Then take some <m>salt</m> and <m>verdigris</m> and soak it with as much of one as of the other in very strong <m>vinegar</m>, and leave it for XX4 hours before using it, and the whole will be soaked. Then spread this liqueur or sauce on the engraved object with a sponge</ab></root>