<root>﻿#ERROR:_Number_of_<m>_and_</m>_unbalanced#


<page>014r</page>


<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f31.item</image>



<div>
<id>p014r_1</id>



<head>For <m>earth</m> walls and rustic construction</head>


<ab>Swallows have taught us this craft by building their nests out of <m>mud</m> mingled with wisps and bits of <m>hay</m> or <m>straw</m> to make it bond. Therefore, in places where <m>stones</m> and <m>bricks</m> are lacking, one can use <m>earth</m> to make walls thick and thin. The best for this is light <m>earth</m>, which does not form clumps when plowed, or better, that which is so to say mingled with sand, because it can be most easily beaten and tamped down. It is true that you have to dampen it and to cut it into clumps with a ditch-spade, and to put and place it in this form. This one lasts more. There is not so much effort and the dryness doesn’t make it split or crack. However there is not everywhere such earth therefore those who live on a good and fertile land, after having drawn with a rope the width and length of their foundations, drive some high poles and rafters in on the edges at each side to support some boards between which they spread the <m>earth</m> to make layers of approximatively one foot thick, mixing it in an <figure>S.S.S</figure> shape with branches of <m>heather</> or similar things, then with three variously shaped beaters they crush and beat it. This one is called the mallet of a triangular shape as A. and it is used firstly to set out the <m>earth</m>. Then one uses another with a pointed block of <m>wood</m> at its ends helved to a big stick and this one is used to properly press the <m>earth</m> at the walls’ ends and edges which sticks to the boards and is called [   ]. The other one is called the paddle and is used to flatten and beat the <m>earth</m> for the last time as it appears in C. Then another <m>earth</m> layer is made and burnt and it is beaten as aforesaid, and so on until the wall is completed then covered with <m>heather</m> and then with <m>earth</m>. Some incorporate <m>bricks</m> ranks within the said wall. They also make walls […] which gives some width to foundations according to how high they want the wall to be. When it is very white it shows that there is some </m>saltpeter</m>, which gunpowder makers take advantage as it falls down.</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>A<figure/></note>




</div></root>