<root>﻿#ERROR:_TITLE_TAGS_EXIST#


#ERROR:_Number_of_<title>_and_</title>_unbalanced#


#ERROR:_Number_of_<head>_and_</head>_unbalanced#


<page>015v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f36.item</image>


<div>
<id>p015v_1</id>
<head>Tablets</head>
<ab>Some are made of <m>boxwood</m> and inlaid with <m>ebony</m>, <m>saunder</m>, <m>ivory</m>, or <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m> like <m>damaskeening</m>. After that you write with a silverpoint and then erase by using a <m>cuttlefish bone</m> to rub them.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_2</id>
<head>Making letters easier to read</head>
<ab>You cut the largest pieces of <m>beryl</m> or <m>crystal</m> round on one side and flat on the other, then you fit it with a little handle and put the flat side on top of the letter</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_3</id>
<head>Stamping</head>
<ab>If you have a  <m>bronze</m> medal and you want to make it very light, make a lead cavity, then spread upon it a thin plate of <m>gold</m>, <m>lead</m> or reheated <m>silver</m>, place your <m>bronze</m> medal on top and hammer it with a wood mallet.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_4</id>
<head>Softening <m>horn</m></head>
<ab>
Those who mount Agnus Deis and make <m>horn</m> circles for certain little boxes soften the said circles by soaking them in hot <m>water</m> and then shape them on a round or oval-shaped triblet.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_5</id>
<head>Ears</head>
<ab>When a defluxion occurs in the ear, be very careful not to put anything in it, and following the proverb, "ears and eyes should only be touched with your elbow". However, to an infected ear, it is good to apply musky <m>cotton</m>, that is to say, cotton kept in <m>musk</m>, which relieves quite well.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p015v_6</id>
<title>Toothache</head>
<ab>Some put a clove of <m>garlic</m> in the ear on the same side as the aching tooth, and after two or three hours they feel better. Others put in their nostril, on the same side as the tooth that hurts, some green skin scraped from the stem of [plant], namely that which is under the grey one that looks like a stem.</ab>
</div></root>