<root>﻿#ERROR:_Number_of_<div>_and_</div>_unbalanced#


<page>023r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f51.image</image>


<div>
<id>p023r_1</id>


<ab>A mortar is made so that it weighs three quintals and carries a cannonball flat on the side from which it must exit and round on the side of the cannon, as if it was a cannonball cut in half. It is two "pans" long. It has to be loaded with xxv lb of powder because it has to be full to the opening and has to fire. Its bottom is not thicker than the opening and is made of one single piece. Its material has to be better than other artillery pieces, and for 4 quintals of fine <m>copper</m> there must only be one quintal of <m>metal</m> so that it absorbs the shock, and so that, when fired with more force, it is more efficient. It has to be used against a door with a large <m>iron</m> cross before of the bullet, and once loaded, it has to be covered with a firmly sewed rough <m>cloth</m> which is completely smeared with <m>turpentine</m>. Four handles must be added to it while it is cast, for it is then easier to place. The <m>iron</m> cross is fixed to the opening with the <m>cloth</m> covering it. The handles have to be held at its opening’s edge, as you can see. To place it, you need three or four <m>iron</m> rods of one "pan" long and as thick as a finger, which have their point like a gimlet, and their body like a screw as they are strongly pulled, and a ring on the other side to turn them with a short stick that fits into the ring. And the rods have to be fixed on the door, not straight, because they would not have any strength, but crooked as if you wanted to fix them towards the middle of the mortar, and to do this the holes of the handles have to be quite large. In that way, the shooting mortar would push the rods back and forth into the door, and would make more damage. Once in place, you must have "<m>bouquarant</m> saucissons" made in this manner: take eight or nine "canes" of "bouquaran" selvage or more if the gap is larger, which have to be as large as four or five fingers, sew it firmly so that it looks like a pipe where a stick as thick as a finger can fit. Fill it completely with good
  
<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
This one is to be put below an undermined tower with its opening towards the top. One casts two large <m>iron</m> rings and, with a stick or two, four men carry it. They are also used for placing within wall breaches but just half a charge is necessary, that is x lb, and fill the rest with some <m>pebbles</m> and <m>cart stones</m>.</note>


<figure>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
</figure>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
It has to be covered entirely with a <m>waxed cloth</m> and rubbed with <m>turpentine</m> and other combustible things. This cover is made to ensure that the bullet does not fall and so that, when the cover is given fire, the powder does not fail. Upon the fuse, you will have to put a good quantity of powder. Some put on the ball a cross of <m>iron</m> which is longer than the mouth of the mortar by two "pans". Others only put the ball.</note></root>