<root>﻿#ERROR:_Number_of_<m>_and_</m>_unbalanced#


<page>038r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f81.image</image>


<div>
<id>p038r_1</id>
<head><m>Sapphire</m></head>


<ab>There are <m>sapphires</m> that we call trellis sapphires, for they are pierced and it is said that a certain king made a certain ornament out of these in a trellis-like form, perhaps similar to the Écrin of Charlemagne, as it is named, in the treasury of <pl>Saint Denis</pl>, in which the gems are set without foil, so as to enjoy its brightness from both sides, and to show their native quality. I have a white one that seems to be rough and pierced, and is all over spotted with blue. I am of the opinion that these spots are artificial and made of <m>taffre</m> or very clear <m>azure enamel</m> fused on the <m>sapphire</m>. <m>Lime</m> corrodes it as it does on <m>beryl</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p038r_2</id>
<head><m>Saffron</m></head>


<ab>It is imitated and increased with half dried marigold leaves, twisted like a thread, and dried in the hottest sun, and this is mixed, and the aforementioned marigold even adds some dye.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p038r_3</id>
<head><m>Sapphire</m></head>


<ab><pro>Stone cutters</pro> sometimes choose old pieces of antique <m>glass</m> in church windows, which are much thicker than those of today and have more natural colors. If it is for <m>sapphire</m>, they chose the beautiful blue and from those parts in which there are no grains, if possible. After cutting it into squares with <m>emeril</m>, they cut it in bevel and polish it. In this way, they imitate very beautiful <m>sapphires</m>. The old <m>azure enamel</m> for <m>silver</m>, when close to <m>aquamarine</m>, was very suitable for imitating <m>sapphires</m>, but you cannot find it anymore. <m>Aquamarines</m> are imitated with white <m>glass</m>, but they take it from the bottom of the glass.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p038r_4</id>
<head><m>Amber</m></head>
<ab>The orangish color in transparent <m>amber</m> and in the denser one is not internal, since it is whitish in the inside. But they acquire this reddish crust with time and usage. This is the reason why those who cut it with a file or on a wheel do not remove this crust. Thus they only polish it, rubbing it with a <m>willow</m> stick or other soft wood dipped into <m>water</m> and sprinkled with <pl>Brittany</pl> <m>tripoli</m>, and it takes a beautiful polish. If the yellow color resembles straw, and you want to increase the color, hang it inside a fireplace that has a lot of <m>soot</m> and smoke, and it will take on a orangish-red color. Try to take the whitest, most transparent one, and put it under <m>dung</m> so as to make it take on a green tone, as you do with the bones. Or either smoke it in a closed space, in <m>safre</m> or <m>manganese</m> smoke and other drugs that you know. Or in <m>urine</m> and <m>distilled vinegar</m> mixed with colors, or in the vapor of <m>aqua fortis</m> boiling in <m>copper</m>, or <m>aqua fortis</m> boiling with <m>silver</m> and <m>sal ammoniac</m>; and some cut the <m>amber</m> with facets on a soft <m>wood</m> wheel with <m>putty</m> instead of <m>emery</m>, and also with <m>jet</m>. The <m>sal ammoniac</m> called <m>Langlois salt</m>
is a mineral salt that resembles <m>marble</m> stone and is a very strong mineral that comes in big pieces, like that of <pl>Ardonne</pl> and <pl>Monserrat</pl>.</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
I have by experimentation that boiling it in <m>lye</m> or <m>corrosive water</m> makes the surface become reddish. And if it is scrubbed with <m>fir</m> and soft <m>wood</m>, rather than being cooled down, it can be easily cut.</note>
</div></root>