<root>﻿#ERROR:_TITLE_TAGS_EXIST#


#ERROR:_Number_of_<title>_and_</title>_unbalanced#


#ERROR:_Number_of_<head>_and_</head>_unbalanced#


<page>039v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f84.image</image>


</div>
<div>
<id>p039v_a1</id>
<head><m>Ename</m>l</head>


<ab><m>Enamel</m> takes more readily to <m>copper</m> than to <m>silver</m>, it is true that the cut has to be deep and rough. <m>Azure</m> in body and the <m>red</m> called gules, white <m>enamel</m> and thick <m>green</m> take [to such metals] very well. After applying the <m>enamel</m>, one gilds the cut foliage. <m>Copper</m> is as hard to cut as pure <m>silver</m> or pistolet <m>gold</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p039v_a2</id>
<head>For laying colors on <m>glass</m><title>


<ab>In order to stop your <m>turpentine</m> colors from running and to make them unified, mix in a little <m>mastic larme</m> together with the <m>turpentine</m>.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p039v_a3</id>
<head>Tracing a story on <m>glass</m></head>


<ab>If you want to trace a story in intaglio on <m>glass</m>, you can do so in different ways. Place your <m>glass</m> pane, as thin as possible<m>,</m> over the printed image, and having cleaned the <m>glass</m> well with <m>lye</m> and <m>ashes</m> so that it is not greasy, trace over the lines visible to you with some <m>oily black</m> or <m>skales black,</m> using a brush, if you want to paint with colors in the manner of <pro>glaziers</pro>, who spread a wash of <m>skales black</m> all over their <m>glasses</m> and then scratch and uncover the areas where they want to apply colors, leaving whatever is necessary for shadows. But if you want to realize gilt stories on <m>glass</m> with a colored background, imitating the taille-basse of <pro>goldsmiths</pro>, gild the whole <m>glass</m> with gummy <m>water</m> or <m>garlic juice</m> or <m>fig-tree milk</m>. Then moisten your printed story with two humid <m>linen cloths</m> and lay it down on your gilt <m>glass</m>, then with a <m>pin</m> hafted to a small <m>stick</m>, follow your story lines as if you wished to pounce it, and thus you will roughly draw it on the gilt <m>glass</m>. And next you will uncover the background and what needs to be cleared using a very sharp <m>steel</m> awl, and retrace precisely the lines and complete your work and make faces and skin colors in <m>pounded silver</m>. Then you will fill the background with <m>enamel azure</m> or <m>verdigris</m> or fine <m>turpentine</m>-soaked <m>laque platte</m>, mixed with a little <m>mastic larme</m> if you want the colors to be more unified and not to flow. Next, apply on the underside of the <m>glass</m> and over the colors a <m>white tin</m> sheet. And once dry, you can cover your <m>tin</m> sheet with color to hide your secret. The <m>tin</m> sheet gives light to the colors. Thus you will be able to paint without</ab></root>