<root>﻿<page>040r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f85.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p039v_a3</id>
<ab>being expert in painting. If your <m>glass</m> pane is curved as taken from the middle part of a jar, it will show better. When you apply your <m>turpentine</m> colors to your <m>glass</m> panes, first put them on a hot tile and, once they are hot, apply your colors and leave them a while on the tile. Then lay down your <m>tin</m> sheet.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p040r_1</id>
<head>Dye</head>
<ab>Some take Lapathium acutum maius, which seems to be rhapontic rhubarb or "vinette", and using the root, which is yellow in summer, they dye threads and similar things.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p040r_2</id>
<head><m>Aqua fortis</m></head>
<ab>For four pounds of <m>aqua fortis</m> matter that is in the retort, some use four ounces of common <m>water</m> in the container, which is better than putting it into the retort. The <m>alum</m> is dried out and calcined so that the <m>water</m> doesn't have as many impurities. Many do it without drying out the <m>alum</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p040r_3</id>
<head><m>Vinegar</m></head>
<ab>It is widely accepted that heating the <m>mineral salt</m> that looks like a block of <m>marble</m> and is called <m><pl>Cardona</pl> salt</m> in Catalonia and on Spain's borders, until it becomes red hot and throwing it red hot or quite hot in <m>wine</m>, turns it into very good <m>vinegar</m>. Some make it with <m>water</m> poured on pomace that has soured after being pressed by <pro>grape pickers</pro>, but it will not keep and spoils in hot and stormy weather.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p040r_4</id>
<head><m>"Vermeilles"</m> buttons</head>
<ab>Because "<m>vermeilles</m>" resist fire, they are cut into lozenges and flat on one side, next they are joined together in a star shape with a paste of ground <m>enamel</m>, which is then melted and the <m>enamel</m> is gilt with <m>gold</m> leaf and then reheated.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p040r_5</id>
<head>Grottos</head>
<ab>To fill any empty place that cannot be hung with rocks, one puts a piece of thick <m>parchment</m> close to the fire, which retracts and crumples. Next it is painted with distemper, then in <m>oil</m>, and then affixed.</ab>
</div></root>