<root>﻿<page>066r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f137.image</image>


<div>
<id>p066r_1</id>
<head>Double coats</head>


<ab>The <pl>Flemish</pl> and others who make paintings by the dozen apply only one coat and finish in the first go. But the colors will soon fade. When they are laid in two times, they do not fade. You must lay them in thinly and scarcely thick in order to blend them well.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066r_2</id> 
<head>Shadows</head>


<ab>For woman: <m>asphaltum</m>, <m>umber</m> and a bit of <m>red lake</m>.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p066r_3</id>
<head>Painting in distemper on <m>wood</m></head>


<ab>Because it is quite unpleasant to paint in distemper on <m>wood</m> and difficult to paint a face well, some distemper their colors with <m>egg white</m> and apply it with a sponge, or mix it with the <m><sup>egg</sup> yolk</m>, <m>water</m>, and beat it strongly with the <m>bark of a fig tree</m>. With this they paint and blend on the <m>wood</m>, as in <m>oil</m>, and this holds the varnish. But this does not last.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066r_4</id>
<head>Colors in <m>oil</m> that are absorbed</head>


<ab>It is best that colors in <m>oil</m> are absorbed, that is to say they do not remain shiny after they are dry because they do not fade. But if in some places they are shiny, it means that the <m>grease of the oil</m> has remained in that part which will make the colors fade. The varnish will hold all this together, unite it and make each part resemble the other.</ab>


<note>
It is necessary that <m>gold</m> color be laid in thickly because if it is clear it will be absorbed and will run.</note>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066r_5</id>
<head>To <m>gild</m> paintings' mouldings with matte <m>gold</m></head>


<ab>See on the other side of this folio this mark: <figure>*</figure></ab>


<ab>The <pl>Flemish</pl> apply one coat of distempered <m>glue</m> on the moulding, then they distemper some <m>lamp black</m> or <m>soot black</m> with this same <m>glue</m> and leave it to dry. They polish the corners of a few Moresque <sup>ornamentations</sup> and paint them with <m>minium</m>, <m>massicot</m>, <m>ocher de ru</m>, and a bit of <m>yellow ocher</m> distempered with greasy <m>oil</m> in which they clean their <m>oil</m> brushes, because the three aforesaid colors are adherent and dry quickly. After that, they apply the <m>gold</m> and then varnish upon it, and it seems to some that by this means all the black is painted in <m>oil</m>. But it will not be good because the <m>gold</m> can be attacked everywhere and not only on the Moresque <sup>ornamentations</sup>. Go back to the top following this <figure>*</figure></ab>


<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>*</figure>
<head>Matte <m>gold</m></head>
It is made with it with <m>massicot</m>, the <m>ore of ochre de ru</m>, and <m>yellow ocher</m>. In order that the composition tends toward <m>gilded</m> <m>gold</m> on the day after it is applied, if you made the underlayer the evening that you made the color, after having <m>gilded</m>, leave it to dry and rest for one day. After that, rub the <m>gilding</m> with a <m>feather</m> and with <m>cotton</m> so that no flaw will remain, then varnish with <pl>Flanders</pl> varnish that you mix with a bit of <m>spirits</m> in order to make it desiccative. The varnish will be dry in an hour. It will enhance the color of <m>gold</m>. And this matte <m>gold</m> is resistant to the rain provided that you rub it, but it must be dry for eight or ten days. <m>Gold</m> color that is made of various colors from the cleaning of <m>oil</m> brushes is not so good and with time it tarnishes the <m>gold</m> as a result of the <m>verdigris</m>. You must not touch the coat made with gold with your fingers because it will prevent it <sup>the <m>verdigris</m></sup> from attacking it. The moulded <m>gold</m> is spoiled if it touches <m>water</m>, but matte <m>gold</m> is resistant in the rain and in <m>water</m>. You must not burnish it because the tooth would remove it. Collect the imperfections and scraps that you have removed with <m>cotton</m> when the <m>gold</m> is dry and you clean it, because an ounce is worth as much as <m>gold</m>. In <pl>Flanders</pl> the women <m>gild</m>. It is more beautiful when it is a little thick but in <pl>France</pl> they beat it too delicately. On <m>canvas</m> and in distemper one <m>gilds</m> with <m>bol</m>, and <m>honey</m>, and a bit of <m>garlic juice</m>. Breathe on the <m>gold</m> color and if it clouds it is quite dry, but if it will not show the vapor of the breath then it is not quite <sup>dry</sup>. You must not <m>gild</m> with matte <m>gold</m> after having <m>gilded</m> but wait one day or one night. Thus, being dry, it will grip the <m>gold</m>. After that, varnish.
</note>
<cont/>
</div></root>