<root>﻿<page>066v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f138.image</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p066r_5</id>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<figure>*</figure>
<ab>To make beautiful matte <m>gold</m> put in a bit of varnish or greasy <m>oil</m>, not the kind that is made from cleaning brushes but the kind that is made greasy in the sun, or mix with <m>ceruse</m>.</ab>
 
<ab>Matte <m>gold</m> of this kind is scarcely less beautiful than the burnished <sup>gold</sup> and lasts longer in the rain and otherwise, and <sup>is</sup> made more quickly. Burnished <m>gold</m> cracks with time and is damaged in the rain.</ab>
 
<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
When <m>gold</m> color starts to adhere, this is a sign that in ten or twelve hours it will be dry and ready for <m>gilding</m>.</note>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066v_1</id>
<head>To prevent the growth of breasts or to diminish ones that are too large</head>


<ab>Take large <m>breads</m> fresh from the oven and split them into two parts, and apply them when they are as hot as possible, and do this 3 times a day, and continue 4 or 5 days. Afterwards make a plaster with <m><pl>Venice</pl> turpentine</m>, or even better, with <m>common turpentine</m>. Mix it with <m>sumac</m>, <m>sloe</m> from bushes, <m>quince seed</m>, <m>pomegranate flower</m>, and <m>leaves of olive trees</m>, and other things similar, cooked and mixed with <m>turpentine</m>. But I forgot that it is necessary, after having applied the hot bread, which softens and makes you sweat, to apply linens soaked with water from a honeycomb, which is to say <m>honey</m> and <m>beeswax</m> extracted all together from the <m>hive</m>. </ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066v_2</id>
<head>To attract <al>pigeons</al></head>


<ab>Make a fricassee in a pan with <m>hempseed oil</m> and give it to the <al>pigeons</al>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<head>Against the bruising of the eyes</head>
<ab>At night, apply on <sup>your eyes</sup> sheets of very delicate <m>lead</m>. Unique remedy.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p066v_4</id>
<head>Brushes</head>


<ab>In order to make them good, cut the <m>hair</m> from the tail of a <al>squirrel</al>, as as much in one take as could be held in a card rolled like a hollow straw. And putting them thus in the aforesaid folded card, tap it and ruffle it so that the <m>hair</m> gathers together and becomes the same length. Put in the middle one or two <m><al>rat</al> whiskers</m>, then grab and hold it tightly between your thumb and index finger, and dip all the tips of <m>hair</m> deeply in <m>water</m>, then, when you approach 
</ab>
<cont/>
</div></root>