<root>﻿<page>092r</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f189.image</image>


</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_a1</id>
<head>Mixture that is easy to melt</head>


<ab>One part <m>soft tin</m>, one part <m>pure lead</m>, one part of <m>bismuth</m> and one part <m>quicksilver</m>. Stop. Make a line and a soldering, so easy to melt. You could almost melt it in a <m>pure tin</m> dish.</ab>
  
</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_a2</id>
<head>Molding a hollow on one side and a relief on the other</head>


<ab>And for this effect, one casts a <m>fine tin</m> medal, which is harder to melt. And since it is pure, we mold with it.  And one leaves it in one half of the box mold and press it inside so that it holds.  Then, thrown in the box mold soldering, the one described above, or something else that melts better than pure tin. In this way, the second medal will melt and mold itself on the first one without damaging it.  But to make this is a better way, soak <m>lamp black</m> in <m>water</m>, and with a brush, apply a thin coat on the medal which is in the box mold, and leave to dry. In this way the medal will not melt at all.</ab>


<ab>But if you have a <m>copper</m> or <m>silver</m> medal, you can leave it in the casting, if you want to cast in <m>lead</m> or <m>tin</m>; but the medal must be a bit warm, because otherwise, the <m>tin</m> will shrink.</ab>


<ab><m>Tin</m> must be cast very hot, to come clean.</ab>


<ab><m>Soft tin</m>, which is the best one for casting, is the one that, when cast en grille is shiny and polished like a mirror and almost looks as if it has been burnished. This <m>tin</m> has no holes like the one that is brittle, and is not shiny as if burnished.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_a3</id>
<head><m>Potin</m></head>


<ab><m>Potin</m>, cast very hot, runs and drips like tin. But it renders the medal whitish and immediately throws out the green, which good substances do not do.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p092r_a4</id>
<head>Molding statues</head>


<ab>Half <m>bourre earth</m>, which <pro>founders</pro> use, and half <m>clay earth</m> makes a very clean mold.</ab></root>