<root>﻿<page>093v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f192.image</image>


</div>
<div>
<id>p093v_a1</id>
<head>Faces [painted] with <m>distemper</m></head>


<ab>Because colors [painted] with <m>distemper</m> dry quickly and one would not have enough time to complete the shadows and touches on the face, one wets the reverse of the face, on <m>canvas,</m> with a <m>wet sponge</m>. Then, with a small brush, one does the shadows, which don't come off. Then one lays the flesh tones, which does not prevent the already painted shadows from showing [through]. And one touches again the more prominent areas with brighter flesh tones. And with another brush one does the shadows in hatching. The strokes [that make up] the shadows do not come off because they are [made] of <m>bistre</m>, which stains the <m>canvas</m> like rust. The said <m>bistre</m> is good for painting the shadows in <m>distemper</m>, for in <m>oil</m> it lacks body and would dry with great difficulty. One should mix the said <m>bistre</m> for shadows with <m>ocher de rux</m> and a little <m>sap green</m>. The best <m>bistre</m> is the fat shiny one from the fireplaces of large kitchens. It is difficult to grind and grates on the <m>marble</m> slab.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p093v_a2</id>
<head><m>Azure</m></head>


<ab><m>Azure enamel</m> always requires washing because the <m>impurities</m> found in the wastewater <sup>would</sup> make it fade. It should always be applied twice, at first very thickly, moving the brush so as to lay it first lengthwise and then across. It is better used on <m>canvas</m>, which absorbs it immediately, than on <m>wood</m>. <m>Varnish</m> restores its brightness, because once absorbed it becomes dark. In order to test it, <pro>painters</pro> bring their palettes to the <pro>grocer's</pro> and distemper and mix it with a little <m>white</m> ground in <m>oil</m>, for in this manner the good one appears typically bright blue, while the bad one is lavender grey. The thinner one is best to work with. It is refined by washing.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p093v_a3</id>
<head><m>Purple</m> and <m>lake</m></head>


<ab>It [<m>purple</m>] is made of <m>blue</m> and [<m>red</m>] l<m>ake</m> which is also tested on the palette with <m>white</m>. That which gives a clear red rose color, slightly purplish, on a <m>polished knife</m> or on <m>glass</m>, is considered beautiful. That which is dark red is not as pleasant.</ab></root>