<root>﻿<page>100v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f206.image</image>


<div>
<id>p100v_1</id>
<head><m>Gemstones</m></head>


<ab>Take some white <m>stones</m> that are found along rivers, in fine sand, and paths, and that are somewhat transparent. If they are perfectly transparent, it will work better. If not, use the best and whitest ones that you can. Calcine them three or 4 times in your "four à vent" and quench them in <m>water</m> or <m>vinegar</m>. Afterward, take a <figure>℥</figure> of them and crush them with a mortar and pestle, both of pure <m>copper</m>, and grind them until they become very fine powder, which is a sign that they [the stones, now finely ground] have taken on enough of the <m>copper</m> to give them a green quality. Then in your <figure>℥</figure> of stones, add in three <figure>℥</figure> of good <m>minium</m>, unadulterated by <m>brick</m> or something else, and strongly grind everything together again in a <m>bronze</m> mortar. And in all of this, add in a "gros" of <m>glass salt</m>, and some and the common people add in <m>sandever</m> that they get from <pro>glassmakers</pro> or <pro>apothecaries</pro>. But <m>alkali salt</m>, as you know, is better. In this way, the vulgar make <m>emeralds</m> by casting them in sand. If you do not have a <m>bronze</m> mortar, grind in a cauldron of pure <m>copper</m>.</ab>
  
<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
One must heat the crucibles before putting anything in them, and must put them in the forge or "four à vent" before making and building up a fire.


<figure>A "four à vent" containing a crucible</figure>
</note>


<note>
<margin>left-center</margin>
They are done in an hour and a half.
</note>


<note>
<margin>left-center</margin>


A "gros" of <m>salt</m> in four <figure>℥</figure> of <m>stones</m> and <m>minium</m>. When they say for <figure>℥</figure>, that is to be understood as a <figure>℥</figure> of body and not <head><m>esmeraulde</m></head> the of  <m>salts</m> and of the <m>minium</m>.
</note>
</div>


<div>
<id>p100v_3</id>
<margin>left-center</margin>
<head><m>Esmeraulde</m></head>
</div>


<div>
<id>p100v_2</id>
<head>For <m>ruby</m> take some <m>gold</m> leaf</head>
 
<ab>Raise your stove by two tiles on each side because more heat is needed to make <m>rubies</m> than is needed for <m>emeralds</m>. And take a <figure>℥</figure> of white, calcined <m>stones</m>, and put it in a <m>glass</m> mortar and, having vigorously ground with a <m>glass</m> pestle, mix in the weight of a grain of <m>gold</m> leaf used by painters for gilding, and grind


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Some say that mixing the <m>gold</m> with <m>stones</m> and <m>saltpeter</m> makes the color of a peach tree.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Some say that the <m>gold</m> has to be cemented several times and then beat into sheets.</note>
</div></root>