<root>﻿#ERROR:_Number_of_<div>_and_</div>_unbalanced#


<page>101r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f207.image</image>


<div>
<id>p100v_2</id>
<ab>again quite strongly, and then add to it three ℥ of <m><m>minium</m></m>, pound again together and put it in the crucible. Cover it with an appropriate <m><m>tile</m></m>, not too thick, so the heat reverberates better. Then put it on the grid of your furnace, after having put a few thick, rounded <m><m>tiles</m></m> under it. Then fill your furnace to the mouth with <m><m>charcoal</m></m>, heaped to the top, and let it glow for a while, and always maintain the heat even, without letting the <m><m>charcoal</m></m> diminish. And for that purpose, make sure that the furnace is heaped full brim and maintain it like this for one day. The first experiment I made only produced a <m><m>yellow mass</m></m> like <m>minium</m> alone when vitrified, with <m><m>gold</m></m> grains, in a mass at the bottom. Try cemented <m>gold</m> together with <m><m>antimony</m></m>.</ab><m>
</m> 
<note>
<margin>top-left</margin>
If you need more heat, put around the mouth of the glowing furnace some <m><m>tiles</m></m> one against the other in order to make the heat reverberate.</note>


<figure>[tiles propped up against one another]</figure>
</div>


<div>
<id>p101r_1</id>
<head><m><m>Topaz</m></m></head>


<ab>The same dose is used for all jewels, which is one weight of <m>calcined <m>pebbles</m></m> with three weights of <m><m>minium</m></m>, all pounded separately in a <m><m>copper</m></m> mortar for <m><m>emeralds</m></m>, and in an <m><m>iron</m></m> mortar for <m><m>topazes</m></m> or <m><m>amber</m> color</m>, with pestles of the same <sup>matter</sup> as the mortars. <m><m>Emeralds</m></m> and <m><m>topazes</m></m> need to be heated at the same temperature, and for an hour and a half, otherwise they could be burnt. <m><m>Rubies</m></m> need more time and stronger <m>heat</m>, and <sup>to be</sup> colored with <m><m>gold</m></m> leaf. I believe that for <m><m>rubies</m></m> <m><m>pumice stone</m></m> or <m><m>fire-stone</m></m> would be better. See <m><m>enamels</m></m>. Instead of pebbles, try also to mix pieces of <m><m>colored glass</m></m> or <m><m>enamels</m></m>. If the mass is not colored enough, pound it further in the <m><m>iron</m></m> mortar.</ab>
 
<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Slightly burnt <m>tartar</m> mixed in makes beautiful yellow, but not much is needed. <m>Sand</m> also makes it more yellow.</note>
</div>
<div>
<id>p101r_2</id>
<head><m>Salt</m> for melting</head>


<ab>Mix some <m><m>saltpeter</m></m> and <m><m>common salt</m></m> and melt them together and throw them onto <m><m>copper</m></m>, molte or "en bain", which purifies it and makes it run marvellously. First you need to decrepitate [?] <m>ordinary salt,</m> which means holding it over strong heat until it crackles no more; or to melt it better, in an air-furnace. Throw it neatly onto a <m>marble</m> <sup>slab</sup>, then pound it and grind it very finely, then put it in a crucible on an equal quantity of <m><m>saltpeter</m></m>. Let them boil and mix them together until</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
It cleans and purifies <m><m>metal</m></m> very well.</note></root>