<root>﻿#ERROR:_Number_of_<div>_and_</div>_unbalanced#


<page>101v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f208.image</image>


the crucible is red. Then throw it on a marble, and you will obtain a white, hard and uniform matter, similar to <m>alabaster</m>, from which you will be able to cast medals which will look like marble; but keep them away from humidity.</ab>
</div>
  
<div>
<id>p101v_1</id>
<head><m>Hyacinth</m></head>


<ab>It is made, like <m>rubies</m>, with <m>gold</m>; but without such intense heat. <m>Rubies</m> need to be heated for a whole day, and if it does not have heat for long enough, you will obtain only reddened varnish.</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Always heat up your crucibles.
</note>


<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
It is believed that rubified <m>antimony</m> makes <m>hyacinth</m>.
</note>
</div>


<div>
<id>p101v_2</id>
<head><m>Topaz</m></head>


<ab>I melted one part of calcinated and pulverized <m>pumice stone</m> with three parts of <m>minium</m>, the stone pulverized in a steel mortar. I obtained a very nice yellow, without any one grain more yellow than the other. It is true that it was quite colorful. I think it would be better to pulverize the <m>pumice</m> in a glass mortar, since it and <m>minium</m> are yellow enough by themselves. I obtained a matter with a nice yellow on top, as I said, and the bottom as a <m>fire-stone</m> without transparency, with which, in mixing in other</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p101v_3</id> 
<head>Varnish</head>


<ab>The Germans boil the <m>minium</m> intensely in <m>linseed oil</m>, and to give it the consistency of varnish, they mix in heavily pulverized <m>yellow amber</m>.</ab>
</div>
 
<div>
<id>p101v_4</id>
<head><m>Ammoniacum</m></head>


<ab>Mix it in small lumps in a little quantity of good <m>vinegar</m>, and heat that up. Then strain it with a cloth strainer. All medicinal <m>gums</m> dissolve in <m>vinegar</m>.</ab>
</div></root>