<root>﻿<page>116r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f237.image</image>


<div>
<id>p166r_1</id>
<head>Casting plants and flower bouquets</head>


<ab> 
One must cast them as soon as they are picked because they wilt and dry out. Dunk them, therefore, right away in good <m>spirits</m> and then put them in your sand mold, soaked like <al>snakes</al>. There is nothing to be released [from the molds] because while the molds are heating up, the plant material burns away, which does not happen with animals, which have bones. For bouquets, the sand must be finer than for <al>snakes</al> because, if it were thick, it would crush the flower.
</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-top</margin> 
<figure/> burn the plants, flowers, and animal parts that are remaining. Afterward, they must be cleaned and the cinder removed. Then reheat them [until] they are red for casting. Reheat in the beginning with some <m>charcoal</m> lit over a gentle fire, and put your core molds down flat on the <m>charcoal</m> encircled by <m>bricks</m>. Molding frames are reheated on a grate.
</note>
</div>


<div>
<id>p116r_2</id>
<head>Core molding the same sand [for] <m>wax</m> images, <m>lead</m> medals, and similar things</head>


<ab>Make sure that these are well emptied. If they are not, fill [them] with <m>wax</m>, which will not be it, and then smear your wax or lead images with a very thin and light layer of olive oil in such a way that the oil does not give any thickness or body to the medal. Then heat it with a little spirits and, when it is lukewarm, wet the oiled medal, because if the water is cold, it will resist the oil. It will not hold on to it. After, cast your <m>plaster</m> sand,<m>matton</m>, and <m>alum</m>. Wet it on top having placed your image on the "mandorle dardile" and having given it some contour to give the necessary thickness. These medals oil and rub against themselves in this way with the spirits because they are firm and hard, and they would not ready to be taken out of the mold, which is resistant like real animals, which are soft and flexible.</ab>


 
<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin> 
When you have soaked your sand, do not cast on the middle of the mold, but on the edge so that the sand gently settles, so that the first <m>cement</m> be clear and thick afterwards. If your soaked sand sizzles like <m>water</m> falling in a mold, it is a sign that it is too light. Make it, then, of an average thickness. 
</note>
</div>


<div>
<id>p116r_3</id> 
<head>Casting <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m></head>


<ab> 
The molds must be fire-red and ablaze when you cast <m>gold</m> or <m>silver</m> in them, or when you burn flowers and bouquets. The gate must not be very big where the thing being cast enters because the matter will flow better without disturbing the mold, and does not become so filled with bubbles. 
</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p116r_4</id>
<head>A way to enamel very fine <m>gold</m> rose leaves and others</head>


<ab> 
After you have cast or beaten in <m>gold</m> the thin leaves of a rose or other things, if you want to enamel them, you must solder or braze your fine, <m>gold</m> leaves onto <m>silver</m> strips, which will strengthen them to support the <m>enamel</m>. After the things has been enameled, put the work in <m>aqua fortis</m>, which will eat away the <m>silver</m> and leave all the <m>gold</m> with its enamel. For this, the <m>gold</m> must have been passed…
</ab>
</div></root>