<root>﻿#ERROR:_ATTRIBUTED_TAGS_PRESENT#


<page>118v</page> 
<image> #ERROR:_INSERT_LINK# </image>


</div>
<div>
<id>p118v_a1</id>
<head>Excellent sand</head>


<ab>Get some of the same sand, the finest that you can, for covering the medal.</ab>


<ab>For the best [result], it is necessary to take sand already used in the core before using it in the box mold, until it can no longer be taken out.</ab>


</div>
<div>
<id>p118v_b2</id>
<head>Casting in a box mold</head>


<ab>The same sand which has been used in composed heated cores, i.e. of plaster, brick and feather alum, is excellent for casting in box molds, and I have tried it as follows. I crushed the pieces which had come out of core molds in a mortar, pestling slowly, because this sand is very soft. I did not pass it through a sieve, because the feather alum mixed in, which makes it bind together, would not pass through. But I did refine upon marble what seemed to me too coarse, and having thus prepared it, I moistened it with the <m>sal ammoniac water</m> made of sal ammoniac the size of two walnuts, in a bottle of common water the size of a bottle in which one boils ground barley, or in a good pot of water. You should find the water fairly salty. I mixed in half a glass of sal ammoniac two silver spoonfuls of spirits. Having thus moistened the sand in order to give it a nice hold, though it still came apart easily, I sprinkled my medal with charcoal pulverized with a file to remove the oil fat, and all other fat. One must avoid these, since they hinder good stripping. I blew on the medal and molded it, and with the female part of the box mold full, I marked and made a line on the back and side of the medal, and on the nearby sand as well. In order that the second box mold take the imprint thereupon to indicate the place for making the cast, I uncovered the contour of the medal and pounced the whole side with pulverized carbon, and then I filled the male part with sand. I separated the box mold and did not strike the corners of the medal to make it strip, since that cracks the sand and makes it come apart. But I did strike the back of the box mold, holding the place of the medal on the bottom, and it molded very cleanly. If it hadn’t stripped thus, I would have waited to remove it until the box molds had been dried out over heat. I lit a row of charcoal between two little trivets of iron in the form that you see [viz. image id="p118_d2" in the left margin], and put the back of the box molds thereupon, and the imprint on top, since in this way, they dry out slowly. And if, by chance, they should crack from being too moistened, it’s on the back that they take the harshest heat, and the imprint remains safe and whole. 
 
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
For medals and flat things, the true heat of lead and tin. That is when it is melted gently.</note>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
Note that I filled the box mold before pressing, and did not strike it, but pressed it with the strength of my hands alone, since striking it may distort it. Make sure that your box mold does not move at all, and if you put some moistened sand under it, it will only hold in place more firmly.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
Make a cast that is not too thick, as not to weigh the medal down, but cast wide enough over the medal that it covers the third part. Do not forget the vents.</note>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
Drying box molds means removing their dampness, so that they do not smoke any longer, though they be very hot.</note>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
To heat is to redden the box mold, which is done for gold and for silver.</note></root>