<root>﻿#ERROR:_Number_of_<div>_and_</div>_unbalanced#


<page>0121r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f248.item</image>


<id>p0120v_4</id>
<ab>a sign that there is some humidity and if the flower was also watery it would rot. Moreover the sand must not be rough because its weight would make the flower lose its original shape. Once you have chosen it accordingly, take a box in which you first make a layer of sand on which you will display the stalk of the flower laid in a way that the flower does not touch nor the bottom nor the edges of the box and stands in the air. Then add more sand on the stalk so that it remains strong and solid. Finally take some of the same sand and sprinkle and subtly display it with two fingers on the flower like the flow of an hourglass. And once the flower is almost covered, strike with your fist the table on which the box is displayed, so that the sand lowers and surrounds everything. Finally cover the entire flower, and lay other flowers, one after the other, as many as the box can hold. Then put the box in warm sun. And as the flower dries, the sand that goes with it continues to press and prevents it from rotting and tightening and consequently, it dries and keeps its original shape. And to do so, make sure to chose boufarcis, marigolds, the yellow meadow’s flowers called rammenlus or palta lupina, amaranth, and similar flowers like broom and others which you will know from experience.</ab></div>




<div>
<id>p121r_1</id>
<head>Keeping fruit over a year</head>


<ab>One has to pick them in a sane and dry weather and should pick by the stalk without touching the fruit with the hand and then put them into <m>glass</m> bottles which have wide necks like <m>glass</m>  jars for jam. Protect them with <m>straw</m> or something else so that they cannot break, and seal the opening with <m>wax</m>. If they had <m>glass</m> lids they would be better. Put the bottles in a box and then put the box in the well, or in the cellar or in a vet or a [illegible] made of <m>earth</m> full of <m>water</m>.</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The sand the goldsmiths use to sand enamels and the white one which the glassworkers use and any type of fine sand which does not have much body, put it through a sieve made of <m>horsehair</m> because this matter must not be very thin. Then dry it well in the sun for  several days in order to remove the dampness and ventilate it as you would do with <m>wheat</m> so that the dust goes away. Once cleaned of dust and dried, use it as you know.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
Pansies can be preserved in the same way.</note>


<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Because there where the hand touches it will rot. Even it is yours not to take it. You can also use vine leaves.</note></div></root>