<root>﻿<page>121v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f248.item.r=</image>

<div>
<id>p121v_a1</id>
<head>Casting in <m>silver</m></head>


<ab>You should place the animals as said and similarly compose the <m>sand</m> by taking four measures of <m>plaster</m>, two measures of annealed <m>bricks</m>, and one measure of annealed <m>stone alum</m>. Mix it well, and once it is ready and you wish to mold, take three measures from the sort of dish used by peasants to eat. Add pure annealed <m>stone alum</m> that has been ground in a mortar to this <m>sand</m>, as much as you will be able to grab with your four fingers and thumb or with a small joincte. Then, mix well and dillute [this mixture] with a bit of <m>sal armoniac</m> and the rest of <m>common water</m>. And stir it with your palette so that it all becomes like a thick sauce or light <m>mustard</m>. Once you have applied <m>spirits</m> with a brush on the animal, cast and swell, and hit the table for the mold to shake and proceed similarly as the others. Do not forget to put <m>crocum</m> because it prevents mold from breaking and it is approriate with every <m>metal</m>.</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Alloyed <m>silver</m>, provided it is soft, is better for casting than pure <m>silver</m>.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
The <m>stone alum</m> should be quite pulverized and mixed.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
<m>Sal armoniac</m> works well with <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m>.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
which should be placed in the dish rather than in the <m>sand</m>, which should be placed in the <m>water</m>, instead of the <m>water</m> poured on the <m>sand</m>. 
</note>


<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<m>Brass</m> is the enemy of <m>gold</m> and works well with<m>silver</m>.</note>


</div>
<div>
<id>p121v_a2</id>
<head><m>Silver</m> [used] to cast</head>


<ab>It is not pure but alloyed <m>silver</m>, and it does not become perfectly white on the fire because they [<pro>goldsmiths</pro>] whiten it after the melting to clean up the welding marks that occur when an animal needs to be attached to another or when it needs repairing. [The process] is similar with teston <m>silver</m> and all alloyed <m>silver</m> as long as it is soft and good.</ab>


<ab>Before starting to cast in <m>silver</m>, in order to coat all round and strengthen your molds, you should use <m>earth</m> that can withstand fire, such as this sandy earth mixed with <m>cloth waste</m> which <pro>founders</pro> use to cast their canons, or any good <m>lute</m> that can withstand fire. They need to all be red and to be tied with <m>iron</m> wire.</ab>


<ab>Rather than anneal the molds, have the mixture necessary so that the <m>silver</m> runs.</ab>


<ab>If <pro>goldsmiths</pro> knew the material to make <m>silver</m> run in their work, they would buy it in quantity. Some buy it five sols for a denier.</ab>
 
<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
I have used <m>silver</m> from the capital.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>left-bottom</margin>
Before luting and strengthening the molds for <m>gold</m> and <m>silver</m> with the said <m>earth</m>, the cast and the vents must be made and the molds must have been annealed and made quite red to burn the animals, flowers and herbs that are inside. The ashes in the molds should be cleaned thoroughly. Once the molds are quite clean and ready, lute them and bind them with <m>iron wire</m>. Anneal them straight away until they are quite red.</note>
</div></root>