<root>﻿#ERROR:_Number_of_<div>_and_</div>_unbalanced#


<page>122v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f251.item</image>


<div>
<id>p122v_1</id>


<head>Cleaning the platter and the spoon you had used to soak sand</head>


<ab>Be very careful and clean quickly the platter and the spoon you used to soak sand after casting while still fresh. Otherwise if it dries it will crumble and fall into your fresh sand when you cast again, and will make holes and damage the work. Also when you heat the mold again little pieces will peel and will not allow you to mold properly. </ab></div>


<div>
<id>p122v_2</id>
<head>Molding hollow</head>


<ab><m>Wax</m> alone cools down too soon and does not spread very well and <m>tallow</m> keeps its heat and spreads everywhere. But <m>tallow</m> alone is not good. But when <m>wax</m> and <m>tallow</m> are mingled the work goes well. <m>Crawfish</m> and bodies of other small animals can easily be mold, but it will not be so easy to mold hollow their legs.</ab>
 
<div>
<id>p122v_3</id>
<head>Molding medals and flat things</head>


<ab>You do not have to make your gate with channels like that <figure/> this way <figure/> and which covers the medal well. Because the one with the channels is only made to fit the more subtle works and the other which is larger and comes in one piece is more suitable for flat medals. But be careful that the casting goes very smoothly to the medal. The cast must not be as thick as the medal if it is as thin as a sheet of paper. And then from the medal close to the gate make it thicker and thicker and it will come out better. If the cast is thick when it enters the medal the work will never be well done. It has to be moderately thick from the middle of the gate to the top and very thin from the middle to the bottom. Do not forget to notch the top of your mold, so that the <m>metal</m> does not spread too fast.</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
The first part of your mold which is the first to be casted on the plate of <m>clay</m>, cracks more easily on fire than [illegible].</note></div></root>