<root>﻿<page>123v</page> 
<image> #ERROR:_INSERT_LINK# </image>


<ab>In the early morning, your lute being dry, put your crucible in an air-furnace, first in low heat, as much to heat your crucible as to give time for the fury of the <m>saltpeter</m> to pass. Then, gradually heat up the fire and, when in full heat, let you matters on it for 12 hours, or a natural day. your crucible on a high fire during 12 hours, or  during one natural day. When you make this mixture, be sure to make a good quantity of it, because the smoke i dangerous to your health, and you want to avoid having to make some often. Instead of working in the morning, eat a buttered toast, and put some of that <m>butter</m>, or <m>zedoary</m>, or some <m>gold</m> coins into your mouth, and bandage your face with a towel under your eyes. You can use the crust of this lump to clear <m>silver</m> when it starts melting. Keep the grain of the lump at the bottom of the crucible, add a bit of this grain to <m>silver</m> when you want to cast. Just as you have added fine tin to <m>copper</m>, and <m>looking-glass tin</m> to <m>lead</m>, and since too much <m>tin</m> and <m>looking-glass tin</m> make <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m> too brittle, similarly too much of this grain made from the matters above mentioned would make your <m>silver</m> too brittle and darken it. The composition above mentioned will last a long time if has been heated a whole day, gently at first, and then under gradually increased heat until the end. Using a load of charcoal, let it consume itself, and let your crucible cool down. Then break it [the mass], you’ll see two hard sheets in the crucible; the upper ones looks stony, being composed of <m>sublimated salts</m> mixed together. The other sheet is metallic, made from <m>aes ustum</m> fillings and <m>antimony</m>, which have very fine grains. Grind the upper sheet, made from <m>salts</m>, and use it to lighten and clean the <m>silver</m>. The metallic grain you will use to mix in the melted metal. </ab>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
charcoal fire</note>
 
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
Or, after you have had your <m>drugs</m> ground by a rustic, put them in your crucible -- the latter being luted, dry and put into the furnace-- have some shop boy, knowledgeable about <m>charcoal</m>, take care of the fire. </note>
 
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
This metallic mass is sold to <pro>goldsmiths</pro> to soften their soldering, because <m>brass</m> exhale when melting. With a little of that matter, they solder over the other soldering.</note></root>