<root>﻿<page>126r</page> 
<image> #ERROR:_INSERT_LINK# </image> 
</div>
<div>
<id>p126r_a1</id>
<head>Molding fruits and animals in sugar</head>


<ab>Sugar is fatty, and, with it, r<m>ound</m> things and large muscles are <m>cast</m> well but fine and delicate things [are cast with] difficulty. However, try well-purified sugar. The plaster mold must be soaked in water for a full night <m>or a</m> full <m>day bef</m>ore casting sugar so tha<m>t it</m> [the mold] is saturated with water and does not <m>soak</m> up the syrup [the sugar mixture]. The [p<m>laste</m>r] mold must also be strip<m>ped v</m>ery we<m>ll fr</m>om it [the sugar], because sugar is sour and brittle. Thus, do not cast anything with sugar <m>whic</m>h is not stripped easily from it, and which can not be <m>neat</m>ly molded in two parts to open as will be needed. If you want to mold a grape, you must get it when it is very fresh; because if it is withered, it [the cast] will look the same. See to it, thus, that you make your molds in the natural season for each thing [fruit]. Grapes that one wants to cast in sugar are man-made, either with wax or earth or with grapes mold<m>ed wi</m>th melted wax, on some dish <m>[p</m>last<m>e &amp; c</m>hose pleine] in a way so that they <m>are</m> pressed closely together and easily stripped from it. And only a half [of the grapes] should be molded. Or, if you have some of those grapes called chauches or sauvignons which have well-pressed grapes, set half of the grapes in the dish of clay, and cast on the other half, and if any grape is not stripp<m>ed f</m>rom it, pluck it out. Note that a grape whose grapes are set apart and separated cannot mold well in either sugar or metal because the ends of the cluster are so fine. Simi<m>larly</m>, if <m>the</m> grape is kept, that it cannot hold the bunched grapes. Therefore, a hollow should be cast, which you will not be capable of if the grape is not close together and without having them spread apart.</ab>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
to cast and brittle, and [it] breaks when dry</note>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
+ In order to mold pears and apples in sugar, do not cast. Rather, fill half of the mold, and then join <m>the</m> two [halves], and keep turning [it] until the sugar is stuck and cold. Do not mix anything in the mold except <m>the r</m>eheated plaster, as you know.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
The mold nee<m>ds to h</m>ave been soaked in cold water for one full day and night and [the mold] must be damp whe<m>n you</m> cast in sugar.</note>
 
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
The sign that the syrup or <m>the m</m>elted sugar has boiled enough in the water for cas<m>ting</m> fruits is when <m>it ma</m>kes threads when shaking i<m>t. An</m>d if it passes this point, it will not be good because it will make [it] damp. If the sugar attacks itself, throw a bit of amidin in the mold or rub i<m>t wit</m>h an almond.</note></root>