<root>﻿<page>142v</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f290.image</image>


<div>
<id>p142v_1</id>


<head>Moulding <al>grasshoppers</al> and other things too thin</head>


<ab>If you have a piece of writing <m>paper</m> to mold, which is very thin, after you have made a first casting and it has taken, add a little thickness to the back of your <m>paper</m> with some melted <m>butter</m>, which is the most appropriate means there is, and <sup>this method applies as well</sup> for strengthening the wings of either a <al>butterfly</al> or <al>grasshopper</al>, or any delicate part of an animal for which you need to add some thickness. Be advised <sup>however</sup> to apply this melted <m>butter</m> underneath the wing or whichever place, so that it is not seen.  To give thickness to a pansy or other flowers, <m>butter</m> is not good, thus <sup>one uses</sup> <m>wheat oil</m>, which dries quickly and holds firm.  <m>Wax</m> would not be appropriate <sup>in this case</sup> because it is too hot, having been melted, and it makes the thing to which it is applied draw in.  But <m>butter</m> is good <sup>to work with</sup> and easy to handle.</ab>
 
<note><margin>left-top</margin>If you write on <m>paper</m> or on <m>cardboard</m>, and your piece of writing has been made with <m>gum</m>, the wetness of the <m>clay</m> pack or of the soaked sand for the noyau will moisten it <sup>and</sup> ruin it.  Thus, write with <m>cinnabar</m> mixed with <m>oil</m>, on oiled and stamped <m>paper</m>.</note>


<note><margin>left-middle</margin><figure>+</figure>Reheat your molds with lighted <m>charcoal</m> first in the forge so that the fire is not too hot and does not break the molds.  And do not put as many coals where the mold is thin as you would do where the mold is thick.</note>
</div>




<div>
<id>p142v_2</id>
<head>Moulds</head>


<ab>Make some notches in them <sup>the molds</sup> that enter more into the inside of the mold than the outside because in this way, they have more strength.  Take care to keep from reheating them suddenly in a burning hot fire, because this will make them break.</ab>


<note><margin>right-middle</margin>Do not keep them <sup>molds</sup> in a humid place, nor an enclosed place if they are not well dry, because they will mold.  The same with dried animals.</note>


<note><margin>left-middle</margin>It is not at all necessary to reheat the molds two times when the animal can pull away without burning, as do <al>toads</al>, which can very well be molded hollow like all thick animals. However, it is always good to redden the mold once.</note>
</div>




<div>
<id>p142v_3</id>
<head><m>Lute</m> for <m>luting</m> your moulds</head>


<ab>I have yet to find a <sup>recipe for lute</sup> that is made more quickly than this one,  nor better. Take some lean <m>earth</m>, <sup>the kind</sup> of which <pro>founders of artillery</pro> and <pro><sup>founders</sup> of bells</pro> use to make their trasseaulx and molds, which is lean and sandy.  Soak it moderately like a very thick <m>mortar</m>. Mix into it about half of its quantity of <m>horse manure</m> and then beat it well.  Afterwards mix in a third part of discarded <m>cloth waste</m> or <m>cloth shavings</m> and beat it well again.  You can reheat your mold as soon as the <m>lute</m> is ready.</ab>
</div></root>