<root><page>039r</page>
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f83.image</image>


<div>
<id>p039r_1</id>
<head><pro>Goldsmith</pro></head>


<ab>They bind <m>silver</m> filings with some <m>saltpeter</m> which refines it without making it sour. But <m>gold</m> filings are bound to <m>borax</m> or, to save the <m>borax</m>, with <m>lead</m>, which refines the <m>gold</m> and makes it softer, because the <m>saltpeter</m> would make it sour, as is not the case for <m>silver</m>. This is why, for the sake of saving, <pro>goldsmiths</pro> use <m>lead</m> to bind <m>gold</m> in order to save <m>borax</m>, which costs 8 sols per ounce and <m>saltpeter</m> costs 10 sols per pound. When <pro>goldsmiths</pro> have thus bound their <m>silver</m> filings with <m>salpeter</m>, the mixture vitrifies into a <m>red enamel</m> in the bottom of the crucible. I do not know if the <m>copper</m> mixed in with the <m>silver</m> is responsible for this. Try for <m>enamel</m>.</ab>
</div>


<div>
<id>p039r_2</id>
<head><m>Dyers woad</m></head>


<ab>It is grown in <pl>Auragnes</pl> where the soil is so fertile that if you grew wheat there every year, it would fall over from the kernels being too full. This is why <m>dyers woad</m> and wheat are cultivated alternately. For cultivating <m>dyers woad</m>, the soil is ploughed with <m>iron</m> shovels like those of gardeners. Then with rakes, clods of earth are broken up and tilled as for the sowing of some vegetable gardens. It is usually sowed on Saint Anthony's day in January. Eight harvests can be made. The first ones are the best. The best of Auragne's <m>dyers woad</m> is the one from <pl>Carmail</pl> and the one from <pl>Auraigne</pl>. And sometimes the <m>dyers woad</m> is good in one field and worthless in another that is closeby. The quality of the <m>dyers woad</m> can be recognized when you put it in your mouth and it tastes like vinegar, or when you crumble and break it, there are silver or golden mold-like veins. It is pressed in the dyers' cistern, and to fill a cistern, six bales are needed. Several <m>wool</m> flocks are kept there. And if it produces 15 dyings, it is said to be worth 15 florins, if it produces 20 dyings, 20 florins. The good kind will dye up to 30 times and usually up to 25 or 26.</ab>
</div></root>