<root><page>140v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f286.item.r=</image>


<div>
<cont/>
<id>p139v_a1</id>


<ab>  
to engrave on <m>silver</m> &amp; <m>copper</m> with aqua fortis. With this [<m>wax</m>] too, one fills the cavity of a relief, &amp; then casts in this cavity, with moistened <m>sand</m>, which immediately takes the relief very neatly. And then you can cast its cavity on it in <m>copper</m>, <m>gold</m>, and <m>silver</m>, and make really singular seals.</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>
Seals</note>


</div>
<div>
<id>p140v_a1</id>
<head>To cast in <m>sulfur</m></head>


<ab>
To make a clean cast in <m>sulfur</m>, arrange the pith of some <m>bread</m> under the brazier, as you know how to do. Mold whatever you want &amp; leave it to dry &amp; you will have a very clean work.</ab>


<note>
<margin>left-top</margin>

Try <m>sulfur</m> passed through melted <m>wax</m>, since it won't catch fire &amp; won't make more little eyes.</note>


</div>
<div>
<id>p140v_a2</id>
<head>Molding and reducing a big piece</head>


<ab>
Mold it with the pith of the bread just out of the oven, or like that aforementioned, &amp; and in drying out it will diminish &amp; by consequence so too the medal that you have cast. You can, in this way, in lengthening out or enlarging the imprinted bread, vary the figure &amp; from one face make several quite different ones. The <m>bread</m> straight from the oven is best. And that which has been reheated twice shrinks more. You can cast <m>sulfur</m> without letting the imprint on the <m>bread</m> dry, if you want to cast it as large as it is. But, if you want to let it diminish, let it dry either more or less.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p140v_a3</id>
<head>Casting of <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m> in <m>plaster</m></head>


<ab>
If you want to cast some flat medal or some animal that is not very heavy, and that must not be burnt inside the mold, you can rather cast in <m>plaster</m> &amp; <m>brique</m> mixed as above; and not in <m>plaster</m> alone, because it will shrink too much feeling a vehement fire if it is not kept from it. But, with the <m>brick</m>, it holds well. In any case, take heed to dry out your mold at length &amp; on a soft fire &amp; with patience, because it has no need of reheating. But when your work is of <m>flowers</m> or other things whose molds need to be reheated &amp; fired, mix the plaster with some <m>stone alum</m> &amp; also with <m>filings</m>. I have molded in <m>plaster</m> &amp; <m>brick</m> very neatly &amp; it has endured many castings.</ab>
 
<note>
<margin>left-</margin>

I tried the <m>plaster</m> &amp; <m>brick</m> alone and molded en noyau with them as with the others. My mold was very clean, having lightly <m>oiled</m> my metal &amp; rubbed it with <m>spirits</m>. I made my casting wide at the entrance, proceeding while making it thin just until the medal is quite slender. I changed the casting which had taken a good hold of the medal. I dried out the mold on a soft fire &amp; at the end, let it really heat up without its turning red. I let it cool to such a degree that I could hold my finger to it without burning myself. I made a line of 4 ℥ of <m>tin</m>, ix deniers of <m>lead</m>. Afterwards I put with 4 ℥ of <m>tin</m>, xii deniers of <m>lead</m>. It is very good &amp; fine.</note>


<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>

When there is nothing to burn inside your mold, it is not necessary to reheat for <m>lead</m> and <m>tin</m>. But for <m>flowers</m> and that which must be burned yes indeed.</note>
</div></root>