<root><page>067v</page> 
<image>http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f140.image</image>
 
<div>
<id>p067v_a1</id>
<head>Files</head>
 
<ab>If these are not tempered in the manner described, packed in <m>soot</m>, <m>salt</m>, and <m>vinegar</m>, they will not be good. The large squared files used by <pro>locksmiths</pro> to draft their work are made of nothing but <m>soft iron</m>. But the fine files should be made of <m>steel</m>. <pro>Founders</pro> who repair <m>brass</m> and <m>copper</m> should have their files be coarse otherwise the <m>copper</m> will fill in the grain of the <m>files</m> which will soon render them [the files] useless. The <m>latten,</m> which is more sour, makes files finer than <m>copper</m>.</ab>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p067v_a2</id>
<head><m>Ox hooves</m> for <m>sand</m></head>
 
<ab>Being well burned two times &amp; pulverized, they mold very cleanly as <m>sand</m> and do not need to be recooked, but just heated with the flame of <m>straw</m>. But if you are doing core molding, apply the first coat very thinly with your brush, and leave it to  dry. Then strengthen the next coats with <m>wadding</m> mixed with this aforementioned <m>sand of bone [hoof]</m> dampened.</ab>
 
<note>
<margin>#ERROR:_NO_MARGIN_AVAILABLE#</margin>
It is the cleanest <m>sand</m> one can find for firing.</note>
 
</div>
<div>
<id>p067v_a3</id>
<head><m>Essential oils</m></head>
 
<ab><m>Walnut oil</m> mixed with the same quantity of <m>turpentine</m> and distilled with an alembic makes an <m>essence</m> that is whiter than common <m>water</m>. But this has no body &amp; does not bind with colors which immediately soak it up, and then leaves the color unable to adhere and it disappears. The [colors] soaked in this way would not let you work with them nor soften them, anymore than tempera would. But you can repair this defect by giving [them] a little body with <m>turpentine</m> [but] not at all as thick as you would use for varnish. And also, in this way, you can make <m>azure enamel,</m> and you can make a perfect <m>lead white</m>. <m>Turpentine varnish</m> made from this <m>oil</m> dries within one hour.</ab>
</div></root>